Good morning. Today we finished the second פרק Perek and move on
to the third פרק. Perek. Our דף Daf today is ל"ו Lamed
Vav 36. We picked up at the bottom of ל"ה עמוד ב׳
Lamed Hey Amud Bet and we were talking about the various stages
of bringing in שבת Shabbat with the שופר shofar blows and the
last issue was addressed was the person who blew the שופר, shofar,
what would he do with his שופר shofar after the blowing, and
it says he had a place to hide it over there on
his roof. And then it ended and we'll pick up with this,
four
lines from the bottom of the page on ל"ה עמוד ב׳. Lamed
Hey Amud Bet. אלא מקום צנוע יש לו לחזן הכנסת בראש גגו,
Ela makom tzanua yesh lo l'chazzan haknesset b'rosh gago, he had a
place of hiding on the top of the
roof, ששם מניח שופרו, shesham maniach shofaro, and there he would place
the שופר shofar after he did the blast, the final blast, לפי
שאין מטלטלין לא את השופר ולא את החצוצרות, l'fi she'ein m'taltalin lo
et hashofar v'lo et hachatzotzrot, because you cannot carry on שבת Shabbat
neither שופר shofar nor חצוצרות. chatzotzrot. Now the word מטלטלין m'taltalin means
like not just carry, you can't carry anything without a עירוב, eruv,
מטלטלין m'taltalin means it's מוקצה. muktzah. So besides the fact that look
he's on the head of a rooftop, that's a רשות היחיד, reshut
hayachid, why does he have to put it away right away? And
maybe he can bring it into the house and other types of
things? No, even if you're totally within a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid,
a שופר shofar and a חצוצרות, chatzotzrot, a trumpet, are מוקצה muktzah
and therefore he had to put it away right away because שבת
Shabbat was coming in in the next second. So now the גמרא
Gemara is going to shift briefly into that discussion about what type
of מוקצה. muktzah. So let's get a
little, make a little progress. ותניא, V'tanya, the one minute we taught
in a ברייתא, Braita, שופר מטלטל וחצוצרות אינו מטלטל. shofar m'taltal v'chatzotzrot
eino m'taltal. We have a ברייתא Braita
that actually makes a distinction, says that you can carry a שופר,
shofar, it's not מוקצה, muktzah, but a trumpet is מוקצה. muktzah. אמר
רב יוסף לא קשיא כאן ביחיד כאן בציבור. Amar Rav Yosef lo
kashya kan b'yachid kan b'tzibbur. There's a difference whether it's private or
public, an individual שופר shofar or a communal one. What's the difference?
So the גמרא Gemara is going to, let's take a look, it'll
be clearer from the way the גמרא Gemara challenges it. The גמרא
Gemara says אמרי ליה אביי, amrei lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye challenged
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, וביחיד דמאי חזי, u'b'yachid demai chazi, why do
you think that it's not a problem if it's a private שופר
shofar because it's fit for something, what's it fit for? חזי לגמעי
בו מים לתינוק, hazi l'gama'ei bo mayim l'tinok, you can use it
as a type of a funnel, you can put water in it
and use the wide end and for somebody to suck out of
the narrow end, a baby.
Put your mouth at the thumb you're doing it.
Well right or you hold the end over, whatever. Anyway, so,
and presumably that's not as possible with a trumpet because since it's
all straight, the water goes straight out, it's not like it gets
caught in the curve and then comes out filters out. I mean
obviously there's a hole you have to like I just said stop
the hole but a trumpet is a lot less usable for that
type of a function. But the גמרא Gemara says okay, we get
the distinction between a שופר shofar and a trumpet, but what's the
distinction between private and public? בציבור נמי, B'tzibbur nami, even if it's
a שול shul שופר shofar which was the case of the blowing
for שבת, Shabbat, חזי לגמעי לתינוק עני, hazi l'gama'ei l'tinok ani, the
שול shul has a responsibility for the poor, so you know, it
could be the שול shul could use it for when a poor
child comes to use it for him. So you know it's not
like the שול shul doesn't have people it needs to use this
for. That's not true, the שול shul does have people it's responsible
for, it's responsible for the poor and therefore it is fit for
even for that, so there's no basis of distinction. ותו, V'tu, and
in addition, הא דתניא, ha d'tanya, we have a third ברייתא. Braita.
So we have one ברייתא Braita that says both are forbidden, second
ברייתא Braita that says שופר shofar yes חצוצרות chatzotzrot no and we
rejected the distinction between public and private. Now the גמרא Gemara says
we have a third ברייתא, Braita, כשם שמטלטלין את השופר כך מטלטלין
את החצוצרות, k'shem shem'taltalin et hashofar kach m'taltalin et hachatzotzrot, that you,
the same way you're allowed to carry a שופר shofar you can
also carry even a trumpet, so none of them are מוקצה. muktzah.
So we have a three-way debate, all are מוקצה, muktzah, none are
מוקצה, muktzah, one is, one isn't. So obviously something's going on here.
So the גמרא Gemara says מני, mani, who is this going like?
אלא לא קשיא, Ela lo kashya, here's the way to reconcile all
three of them. הא רבי יהודה הא רבי שמעון הא רבי נחמיה.
Ha Rabbi Yehuda Ha Rabbi Shimon Ha Rabbi Nechemya.
This is רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, this one is רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, this one is רבי נחמיה. Rabbi Nechemya. Now there you go,
there's your answer.
So, so you have to understand that there are other debates going
on. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is the basic one who holds of
מוקצה. muktzah. One minute, let me just check one thing about רש"י.
Rashi. Right,
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda holds of the standard מוקצה, muktzah, okay, and
therefore he, but he says he makes a distinction between the שופר
shofar and the חצוצרות chatzotzrot for the reason we said that the
שופר shofar is relatively usable and I'll get into being more precise
in a minute but let's just lay it out, and the חצוצרות
chatzotzrot is not and therefore the חצוצרות chatzotzrot is מוקצה muktzah and
the שופר shofar is not. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon basically rejects most
categories of מוקצה. muktzah. And he only has very narrow categories like
מוקצה מחמת מיאוס muktzah machmat mi'us and so on. So even though
the חצוצרות chatzotzrot is normally used for a non-, let's at least
start with this, what's the problem? These are used for things you're
not allowed to do on
שבת. Shabbat. I mean, first let me present it רש״י's Rashi's way.
Okay, so it's a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli shemelachto l'issur. So therefore
they should all be no good. But comes along רבי יהודה Rebi
Yehuda and רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda says, you know what, a שופר
shofar is not so much of a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto
l'issur because it has an acceptable use. ראוי לגמע בו מים לתינוק,
ra'uy l'gam'ei bo mayim l'tinok, so it's a little bit of a
כלי שמלאכתו להיתר. kli shemelachto l'heter. Maybe that's one of its uses
and so maybe it's כלי שמלאכתו להיתר. kli shemelachto l'heter. That's a
שופר. shofar. חצוצרות chatzotzros doesn't really have a good legitimate other use,
and therefore it's a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto l'issur and you
can't carry it. That would be רבי יהודה. Rebi Yehuda. רבי שמעון
Rebi Shimon would reject the whole thing and he doesn't care about
the כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto l'issur or כלי שמלאכתו להיתר kli
shemelachto l'heter and he has no problem with carrying it and רבי
נחמיה Rebi Nechemiah is a one that basically has a much, much
more limited view, and רבי נחמיה Rebi Nechemiah says even a כלי,
kli, you know, that you can only move a כלי kli for
its basic purpose. So the basic purpose of a שופר shofar even
if it can also be used for a legitimate purpose, the basic
use of a שופר shofar is to blow it and use it
as a musical instrument and therefore you can't even move a שופר.
shofar. So basically this is a range of positions about how much
how broad or narrow category of מוקצה muktzeh we have. רבי שמעון
Rebi Shimon has a very small category of מוקצה, muktzeh, so both
שופר shofar and חצוצרות chatzotzros are okay. רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda has
a middle level category of מוקצה, muktzeh, something, you know, broader than
רבי שמעון, Rebi Shimon, so חצוצרות chatzotzros is מוקצה, muktzeh, שופר shofar
is not. And רבי נחמיה Rebi Nechemiah says that even if the
object is maybe per se not מוקצה, muktzeh, רבי נחמיה Rebi Nechemiah
says you can only move objects for their fundamental intended purpose and
therefore you can't even use שופר shofar because its fundamental purpose is
actually using it as a musical instrument which is not allowed on
שבת. Shabbos. So that's the way that רש״י Rashi says. Just one
minute. I want to just lay out a difference here. So if
you take a look, let's actually look because we have it's a
very small page, so we'll take a look at a minute look
at רש״י. Rashi. In תוספות. Tosafos. A lot of big תוספות. Tosafos.
Take a look at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says
towards the bottom of רש״י Rashi at ל״ה ע״ב, lamed hey amud
beis, חצוצרות, chatzotzros, רש״י Rashi says פשוטה, peshuta, it's straight, ואין ראויה
אלא לתקוע, v'ein ra'uya ela litko'a, so it's a דבר שמלאכתו לאיסור,
davar shemelachto l'issur, איסור משום מוקצה. issur mishum muktzeh. So
according to רש״י, Rashi, the fact that you can use the שופר
shofar for a תינוק, tinok, according to at least רבי יהודה, Rebi
Yehuda, makes it a כלי שמלאכתו להיתר. kli shemelachto l'heter. Because
now that's not normally what we would say. We would normally say
a שופר shofar is a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור, kli shemelachto l'issur, but
you can use it in an acceptable way. Take for example a
hammer. You can use a hammer to crack nuts on שבת. Shabbos.
It's not because we're saying that a hammer is not a כלי
שמלאכתו לאיסור, kli shemelachto l'issur, it fundamentally is, it's used for nails,
you can't bang nails on שבת. Shabbos. But you can use a
כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto l'issur for a צורך היתר. tzorech heter.
That's our general rule. You can use a hammer to crack a
nut. Okay, but the problem applying that in this גמרא Gemara is
that, you know, then why not use a חצוצרות chatzotzros for a
מלאכת היתר? melachas heter? So רש״י Rashi seems to be saying, okay
fine, so let's assume that's not what's being said. What's being said
is according to רבי יהודה, Rebi Yehuda, the שופר shofar actually becomes
a
כלי שמלאכתו להיתר. kli shemelachto l'heter. That's enough of a legitimate alternative
use, it becomes a כלי שמלאכתו להיתר. kli shemelachto l'heter. So according
to רש״י... Rashi... The hammer too? No, not the hammer but the
שופר. shofar. That's exactly the difference. Hammer's much more fundamentally used for
איסור. issur. שופר shofar is more malleable. So therefore רש״י Rashi is
saying that the position of רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda is that a
שופר shofar becomes a כלי שמלאכתו להיתר. kli shemelachto l'heter. רבי שמעון
Rebi Shimon isn't even bothered with all of these categories at all,
he says it's all okay, and רבי נחמיה Rebi Nechemiah says you
can only use it for its intended purpose. Okay.
Now that's רש״י. Rashi. Now תוספות, Tosafos, let me just check one
thing.
Right. תוספות Tosafos disagree, right? תוספות Tosafos says, what are you talking
about? You're allowed to use a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto l'issur
with צורך היתר tzorech heter like I just said. So if you
look at תוספות, Tosafos, so that's what he says. Yeah, רבי יהודה
Rebi Yehuda says it's totally fine, the שופר shofar is כלי שמלאכתו
לאיסור, kli shemelachto l'issur, but you can use it as a מלאכת
היתר, melachas heter, so why not חצוצרות? chatzotzros? So look at the
last line of תוספות ל״ה ע״ב, Tosafos lamed hey amud beis, ויש
לומר דחצוצרות מוקצות יותר משופר כמו שפירש, v'yesh lomar d'chatzotzros muktzayose yoser
mishofar kmo she'piraish,
and
then he doesn't help us to see where he's explained it. So
what he
says is, the end of the תוספות הא רבי יהודה, Tosafos ha-Rebi
Yehuda, the first רבי יהודה, Rebi Yehuda, about five lines before the
next תוספות, Tosafos, five lines before the line starts to get wide,
it says like this.
The line starts with the word בשבת, b'Shabbat, maybe seven lines before
it gets wide. אבל בחצוצרות אסור משום דכיון דלא חזי למלאכת היתר
אלא מעט מקצה ליה לגמרי ממלאכת היתר והוי כמיטה שיחדה למעות וניחא
לעמיה מאות. aval b'chatzotzros assur mishum d'keivan d'lo chazei l'melachas heter ela
me'at makzei lei legamrei m'melachas heter v'havaei k'mitah she'yichda l'ma'os v'neecha l'am'a
m'ot. So
basically the problem is like this. We would say both a שופר
shofar and a חצוצרות chatzotzros are כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto l'issur
and as long as you're using it לצורך היתר l'tzorech heter it's
fine. What is the basis of the גמרא Gemara to distinguish them?
So what רש״י Rashi does is he turns the שופר shofar into
a כלי שמלאכתו להיתר. kli shemelachto l'heter. The היתר heter is enough
of a legitimate use that it's actually considered not so much a
כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור, kli shemelachto l'issur, it's a כלי שמלאכתו להיתר. kli
shemelachto l'heter. That's why רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda is okay with it.
What תוספות Tosafos does is he says no, no, no. They're both
כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto l'issur but it's okay to move the
שופר shofar because you're moving it with צורך היתר tzorech heter like
the hammer to crack nuts. So why can't you move the חצוצרות?
chatzotzros? So what he does is he takes the חצוצרות... chatzotzros... So
why can't you move the חצוצרות? chatzotzros? So what he does is
he takes the חצוצרות chatzotzros and he puts it in—he—רש״י Rashi recategorizes
שופר, shofar, תוספות Tosafos recategorizes חצוצרות. chatzotzros. חצוצרות chatzotzros is something that
you would never think of using for anything else. Sure, that's what
I'm going to do. I'm going to take my trumpet and, I
don't know, crack a nut with it, right? Never. And therefore it
becomes more than just a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור, k'li shemilachto l'issur, it
becomes something which is like you're מוקצה לגמרי. muktzeh l'gamrei. You totally
put, you know, will never use it for any other type of
a purpose. So maybe, you know, this, what category does it fall
into? We have categories like מוקצה מחמת חסרון כיס, muktzeh machmat chisron
kis, you're afraid because of its value you don't want to damage
it, but the point is, is that you completely rule out other
usage and therefore it does not have the ability to be used
for other things. Okay? So basically these two, normally we would put
them the same, the גמרא's Gemara distinguishing, is splitting them. So רש״י
Rashi does it by reframing שופר shofar as a כלי שמלאכתו להיתר.
k'li shemilachto l'heter. תוספות Tosafos does it by reframing חצוצרות chatzotzros as
a, no longer in the category of כלי, k'li, it's something that
you completely set, you know, remove from all other purposes. Yeah.
I'm having trouble understanding this. I still don't see how it's different
than a hammer. Because, was it, was it one of these societal
things at the time? Did they really use it all the time
for funnels? Because I'd be much more likely to use a hammer
to crack a nut than a שופר shofar for a funnel.
Okay, so I don't know the answer, which is, that's what's obviously
bothering תוספות, Tosafos, which is why it's harder for תוספות Tosafos to
think that you really can recategorize שופר. shofar. So yeah.
And is it, and is it also one of these things where
it can be like, you know, far-fetched or, or does it have
to be sort of, you know, immediate? You know what I mean?
Like for instance again the hammer, right? Most of us probably wouldn't
use it to crack nuts, but it really is, you know, it
does make, it does make a bunch of sense relative to something
else. So can I use, whatever it is for whatever else it
is?
No, no, no, no, no. It doesn't matter. It's not like you
have to be able to anticipate what that use was. As long
as, you know, you know that you can use your hammer for,
it's not in this category like תוספות Tosafos puts the trumpet where
it's like I would never think of using it for anything else.
As long as, yeah, sure, like a hammer's a tool and if
I, whatever use I wind up needing it for, I'll use it.
And even if I didn't think of that before שבת? Shabbos?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. No, no. It's not that you have to plan
what you're using it for. It's as long as you did not
rule it off limits, then it's open for other uses.
And one final question. I thought the problem wasn't as much with,
with the music, which would make it, I thought the other problem
was you're really worried they're going to מתקן metaken something, right? So,
so is it, so is it really a
מלאכה דאורייתא melacha d'Oraisa or is it? No, no, no, no. Yeah.
That's the reason for the גזירה, gzera, but the הלכה halacha is
you're not allowed to play musical instruments. What you're saying is the
reason for it. That's what motivated the גזירה, gzera, but הלכה halacha
is you're not allowed to play musical instruments.
Yes, is there a difference between רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos whether
or not you can have a hammer, you can use a hammer
for, to crack a nut? Like would that be a נפקא מינה?
nafka mina?
No, because they both say,
no, you mean you point out according to רש״י Rashi who cares
that the חצוצרות chatzotzros is a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור k'li shemilachto l'issur
as long as you want to use it לצורך גופו? l'tzorech gufo?
Right? That's your question according to רש״י. Rashi. Meaning, well, oh, actually
I got confused.
I thought, I thought רש״י Rashi would say that no matter what
because the normal use for a hammer is, it's מוקצה, muktzeh, it's
therefore, therefore
I can never use it.
But, right, right, right. No, no, no, that's what I said. Right,
right. No, no. So it's not clear from רש״י. Rashi. Meaning the
גמרות Gemoras are clear that you can use a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור
לצורך גופו. k'li shemilachto l'issur l'tzorech gufo. So רש״י Rashi presumably is
not debating here. It's possible that רש״י Rashi understands that this גמרא
Gemara where it's talking about the context of you're, you know, moving
the שופר shofar or the חצוצרות chatzotzros and you're going to put
it away, that's not using it לצורך גופו. l'tzorech gufo. That's what's
called מחמה לצל. mechama l'tzel. So the basic הלכה halacha is the
following. You can use a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור k'li shemilachto l'issur if
you, you can move it if you need its space, you can
move it if you need to use it, like to crack nuts.
You cannot use it for its own sake. You cannot use it
to protect it, to put it away so it doesn't get damaged,
to put it away so it doesn't get stolen. So your question
is why, and that's an important point, you left your hammer out
in the yard, it's about to rain, you cannot move it inside
to protect it from the rain. What you can do is all
of a sudden discover a real great need to eat some nuts.
But you cannot move it inside for the sake of the rain.
So רש״י, Rashi, so, and presumably רש״י Rashi does not debate that.
That's a very clear גמרא. Gemara. So the point is, so you're
asking why does רש״י Rashi have to say the חצוצרות chatzotzros because
it's מלאכתו לאיסור milachto l'issur you can't move it at all? What
about moving it לצורך, tzorech, you know, for doing a מלאכת היתר?
melachat heter? And presumably the answer might be he's assuming the case
in, the case is about the, you know, that you blew the
שופר shofar right before שבת Shabbos and you're going to put it
away, that you're moving it to protect it. And moving it to
protect it is something that you could not do with a כלי
שמלאכתו לאיסור. k'li shemilachto l'issur. So I do not believe that there
is a bigger debate here between רש״י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafos. I
believe it's just a question about how they explain this local case.
Is that clear? Right תוספות Tosafos says the case is even moving
it to use a מלאכת היתר, melachat heter, and therefore for תוספות
Tosafos you have to make the חצוצרות chatzotzros totally מוקצה לגמרי. muktzeh
l'gamrei. רש״י Rashi presumably understands the case is you're moving it to
protect it and therefore that would not be allowed, and therefore he
has to make the שופר shofar into not even a כלי שמלאכתו
לאיסור. k'li shemilachto l'issur. Alright? Okay. Yeah, one last question because I
think we're getting a little bit too caught up, but go ahead.
So Rabbi, this is all discussing רבי יהודה's Rebbe Yehuda opinion. This
doesn't come up for רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon or רבי נחמיה Rebbe
Nechemia because they don't distinguish between
it?
Right. Right. Well, well, no. Right, correct. And now the תוספות Tosfot
does point out though, in that regard, that that even רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon who says neither of them are מוקצה muktzah would still
mean that you cannot move it מחמה לצל, mechama l'tzel, you cannot
move it to protect it for its own sake. Okay, so it
gets a little bit, you know, exactly drawing exactly where the lines
of distinction are starts to become a little fuzzier, okay? So תוספות
Tosfot but anyway תוספות Tosfot says let's just read this תוספות'ס Tosfot's
way, okay? And we'll just end with that because it's we're getting
a little caught up in the details. So according to תוספות, Tosfot,
the point is here
that why can you okay why that you you're trying to move
it for a לצורך היתר, tzorach heter, like to do something legitimate
with it like crack nuts or you know use it as a
funnel, so a שופר shofar you so according to רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda a שופר shofar you can a חצוצרות chatzotzros you can't, why
not? Because a חצוצרות chatzotzros is not just a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור,
kli shem'lachto l'issur, it's something you totally set aside. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says both of them you can because both of them are
כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור, kli shem'lachto l'issur, I don't set I'm not I
don't acknowledge that you totally set aside חצוצרות, chatzotzros, I don't have...
שמלאכתו, shem'lachto, yeah,
מלאכתו לאיסור, m'lachto l'issur, meaning they're both מלאכתו לאיסור m'lachto l'issur that
I'll admit because you're musical instruments, but I do not acknowledge that
I do not acknowledge that a חצוצרות chatzotzros is worse because I
don't believe that there's this category of totally setting aside for me
something to be real מוקצה, muktzah, not just כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli
shem'lachto l'issur. כלי kli but something to be real מוקצה, muktzah, fully
set aside and off limits is only a very narrow category. So
therefore both of them I categorize as כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור, kli shem'lachto
l'issur, and therefore both of them you can move לצורך היתר. l'tzorach
heter. You can't move them to protect them, but both of them
you can move לצורך היתר. l'tzorach heter. That's what רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says, and comes along רבי נחמיה Rebbe Nechemia and רבי נחמיה
Rebbe Nechemia says you can't even move them לצורך היתר, l'tzorach heter,
you can only move them for their designated purpose, and since their
designated purpose is איסור, issur, musical instruments, therefore you cannot move either
of them. Okay, so that's the debate. רבי נחמיה Rebbe Nechemia you
can only move things for their designated purpose, so that makes both
of these off limits, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says they're both
כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור, kli shem'lachto l'issur, so therefore you can move them
both for a legitimate purpose, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says the
חצוצרות chatzotzros is worse than a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור, kli shem'lachto l'issur,
it is totally set off limits and therefore you cannot move it.
So this would be רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon talking about the
שופר shofar and חצוצרות chatzotzros is רבי נחמיה. Rebbe Nechemia. Yeah, exactly.
Let's move on. Yeah okay let's just move on a little bit,
okay, fine. The גמרא Gemara says like this: ומאי שופר נמי חצוצרות.
U'mai shofar nami chatzotzros. Now by the way, which is a little
funny, what when we say שופר, shofar, we really mean חצוצרות, chatzotzros,
now what does that mean, I mean there's a שופר shofar and
חצוצרות. chatzotzros. So it means that we're going to see in a
minute that the names got switched. רש"י Rashi says what's bothering the
גמרא Gemara is that in the last ברייתא braisa it says אין
מטלטלין לא את השופר ולא את החצוצרות, ain m'taltalin lo es hashofar
v'lo es hachatzotzros, the order is wrong, right, if שופר shofar is
the thing that is more obvious that you should be able to
carry, as soon as you said לא את השופר, lo es hashofar,
you can't carry a שופר, shofar, well of course you can't carry
a חצוצרות, chatzotzros, so why did we put it in that order?
Now that's normally not such a big deal, we say זו ואין
צריך לומר זו, zu v'ain tzarich lomar zu, anyway, that is what
he says is bothering the גמרא Gemara and the גמרא Gemara feels
a need now, maybe nothing is bothering the גמרא, Gemara, maybe the
גמרא Gemara just feels that this is a good opportunity to point
out a certain fact that there was a name change between שופר
shofar and חצוצרות. chatzotzros. So let's take a look. It says by
the way what שופר shofar really means is what we would call
חצוצרות, chatzotzros, why? And חצוצרות chatzotzros is what we call שופר. shofar.
כדאמר רב חסדא. Kediv Rav Chisda. אמר רב חסדא הני תלת מילי
שנו שמייהו מאיחר בית המקדש. Amar Rav Chisda hani tlata mili shani
shmaiyahu mi-ichar Beis Hamikdash. The following three things the names got flipped
after the destruction of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. חצוצרות שופרא שופרא
חצוצרות, Chatzotzros shofra, shofra chatzotzros, what we used to call a חצוצרות
chatzotzros now we call a שופר shofar and שופר shofar חצוצרות. chatzotzros.
Now that's not for us, right, because we don't speak Hebrew as
a, I mean even if we did speak Hebrew but anyway we
only look at a trumpet and say ah there's a חצוצרות. chatzotzros.
So we only use a שופר shofar and we
use it in its original meaning which is the horn of an
animal made into a musical instrument into a horn, but in the
גמרא Gemara they said that actually they started calling a שופר shofar
a sort of like you know a fashioned metal instrument like a
trumpet and they started calling a חצוצרות chatzotzros what we call a
שופר. shofar. The names got flipped. Okay. By the way, an interesting
example is that if you look in the שאילתות, Sheiltos, which is
גאוני Gaonic work, written in I believe the seventh century, anyway, where
he had like a commentary on the תורה Torah where he discusses
like a little דרשה drasha and then he discusses הלכות halachos relating
to the פרשה, parsha, anyway when he speaks about the מצוה mitzvah
of תקיעת שופר, tekias shofar, he says דמחייבין דבית ישראל למיתקע בחצוצרות.
d'michayvin d'Beis Yisrael l'midka b'chatzotzros. So you're obligated to blow in a
חצוצרות chatzotzros on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. So basically because חצוצרות chatzotzros
meant then שופר. shofar. Okay so these things switched their names. So
למאי נפקא מינה, l'mai nafka mina, what do I care? To שופר
shofar של ראש השנה, shel Rosh Hashanah, so that if somebody says
what do I use for blowing what should I get for ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah you say get a חצוצרות chatzotzros so they don't
go and get a שופר shofar because you're talking fancy biblical Hebrew
and the guy goes and he gets a trumpet. So therefore it's
important to know what the vernacular is and important to know that
when you're talking the vernacular you should tell people go use a
חצוצרות. chatzotzros. yes anyway so now that's one thing that's what's-his-name ערבה
צפצפה צפצפה ערבה, Aravah Tziptzafah Tziptzafah Aravah, what we what used to
be called an ערבה Aravah which is what ערבי נחל Arvei Nachal
used for the לולב Lulav is now called a צפצפה. Tziptzafah. And
what is another type of a plant that's not כשר Kosher for
for the לולב Lulav and what used to be called a צפצפה
Tziptzafah is now called an ערבה. Aravah. So again we call only
the we keep the original terminology, but at that time the names
had switched. So גמרא Gemara says למי נפקא מינה? Lemai Nafka Mina?
ללולב. Lelulav. What difference does it make for לולב? Lulav? Somebody says
what should I use for my לולב, Lulav, you got to understand
that now in the vernacular you should tell him צפצפה Tziptzafah because
if you tell him ערבה Aravah he's going to use the wrong
thing.
Okay. פתורא פתורתא פתורתא פתורא. Psora Psorta Psorta Psora. Big these are
words for like a big table and a small table. So and
they got flipped. Which meant what? So the גמרא Gemara says למי
נפקא מינה Lemai Nafka Mina what do I care about that? What's
called a big table a small table? למקח וממכר Lemikach Umimkar for
business. That if you're saying you're buying a פתורא, Psora, you better
know whether it means a big table or a small table. So
you got to know the vernacular. Okay. אמר אביי Amar Abaye said
אביי, Abaye, אף אנן נמי Af Anan Nami we'll also once we're
giving these lists I'll add something to this list. הובלילא בי
כסי בי כסי הובלילא. Hovlila Bei Kasei Bei Kasei Hovlila. So a
stomach that used to be called a הובלילא Hovlila is now called
the בית הכוסות. Beit Hakosot. And what used to be called the
בית הכוסות Beit Hakosot is now called the הובלילא. Hovlila. So no
yeah these are stomachs of a
cow. Okay. So I don't know how they translate them, but what
do you got there in the English for the הובלילא Hovlila and
the בית
הכוסות?
Beit
Hakosot? Don't translate. They don't translate. Very good. Okay
anyway. So the point is like this.
So the הובלילא Hovlila it was called by the way the other
word for the הובלילא Hovlila was the המסס Hamesas and basically what
that would do is is that that would be like a cow's
their stomach have these essentially stones in their stomach that grind the
food, right? And then it's so that would be the that would
be the הובלילא Hovlila which and had a thin wall and that's
where the grinding of the food would take place. The בית הכוסות
Beit Hakosot would be where the food would go afterwards, it would
sort of be at the end of the cow's like four stomachs,
one of the last stomachs, and that would have very thick walls
and actually doubled over walls with like a fat layer between them.
And that's the בית הכוסות. Beit Hakosot. What this matters for is
for טרפות Treifos because since one has a thicker stomach, a hole
in part of the wall of the stomach is less of an
issue than if the wall is very thin. So that's what the
גמרא Gemara says למי נפקא מינה Lemai Nafka Mina what difference does
it make? למחט שנמצאת בעובי בית הכוסות. Lemachat Shenimtzeit Beovi Beit Hakosot.
If there's a a needle found in the thickness of the wall
of the בית הכוסות, Beit Hakosot, מצד אחד כשרה ומשני צדדים טרפה.
Mitzad Echad Kesherah Umishnei Tzedadim Treifah. If it's only piercing through one
side of the wall it's okay because the wall actually the two
walls there's also a fat layer between them. It's a double wall
held together by a fat layer and therefore even if there's a
hole just in one wall it'll be sealed by the fat layer.
Whereas if the hole pierces through all the way into the second
wall then it won't be able to be effectively sealed. So there
you actually have a leniency that it's not a problem of טרפה
Treifah until it goes through to the second wall. Whereas in the
first stomach where the grinding occurs the wall is very thin and
there's no fat layer and even a hole through you know the
outer whatever there is no first wall but anyway even a hole
you know in that one wall is itself a problem. So that's
the הלכה, Halacha, there's a big difference between those stomachs. And you
have to know what the vernacular is because if you tell somebody
oh yeah it's in the you know הובלילא Hovlila so it's a
it's a problem or it's in the בית הכוסות Beit Hakosot and
it's not a problem. And you're thinking the old terminology and really
the new terminology and he gets it completely mixed up and he
misinterprets it. So you have to be very careful again to know
the vernacular so does not lead to a misunderstanding. Okay. אמר רב
אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, אף אנן נמי Af Anan Nami so let's
get a final let's throw in another one.
בבל בורסיף בורסיף בבל. Bavel Borsif Borsif Bavel. What used to be
called בבל Bavel is now called בורסיף, Borsif, what used to be
called בורסיף Borsif is now called בבל. Bavel. So the גמרא Gemara
says למי נפקא מינה Lemai Nafka Mina what do I care about
this?
לגיטי נשים. Legittei Nashim. For a גט Get for women. What does
that mean? So רש"י Rashi has two explanations. One explanation is the
very first משנה Mishnah in גיטין Gittin is if you bring a
גט Get from מדינת הים Medinat Hayam from the you know the
the islands or whatever the far away places across the sea then
you
have to make a special declaration בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. Bifnai Nichtav
Ubifnai Nechtam. It was written and signed in front of me because
we don't trust that it was necessarily processed properly outside of ישראל
Yisrael that they know the הלכה Halacha and they're careful about various
things. However the גמרא Gemara clarifies that in בבל Bavel if you're
bringing it from בבל Bavel we know in בבל Bavel that they
do know what to do so you do not have to make
that declaration. So now it's important to know what land is considered
בבל Bavel and what land is considered not בבל. Bavel. So what
used to be called בבל Bavel is now called בורסיף, Borsif, what
used to be called בורסיף Borsif is now called בבל. Bavel. So
now the question is is the guy coming from בורסיף Borsif or
not, now is he coming from בבל Bavel or not. Okay so
that's one explanation רש"י Rashi said. The other explanation is just since
you have to mention where people came from and you have to
mention the names of their city, so therefore you have to know
that now these things are being called a different name. However תוספות
Tosafot takes strong exception to that because תוספות Tosafot says בבל Bavel
is It's not a city, בבל Bavel is a country, and if
you look at the last line of תוספות Tosafot נפקא מינה, Nafka
mina, תוספות Tosafot says there's no עיר דשמה ir deshma בבל, Bavel,
there's no city that's named as בבל Bavel אלא מדינהו ela medinahu
ואין כותבין שם מדינה בגט. ve-en kotvim shem medina be-get. You do
not write the name of a country in a גט. get. So
that becomes a question nowadays, you know, and also some people certainly
don't write like ארצות הברית דאמריקא Artzot HaBrit de-America or you know,
what have you know,
which is clearly the שם מדינה, shem medina, but even New York,
New York is a שם מדינה, shem medina, it's not the city,
and so on. So anyway, that's an interesting question. What would be
so bad about it? It's just extra identification. Is תוספות Tosafot saying
we're not allowed to or is he just saying as a practice
we don't, you don't need to. Anyway, we'll worry about that when
we get to גיטין, Gittin, we'll worry about that when we get
to כתובות. Ketubot. הדרן עלך במה מדליקין. Hadran Alach Bama Madlikin. So
that is the end of the second פרק perek with that interesting
little digression. You want to ask something, David, about the shoes from
before? All right, fine.
Can we cover the hammer at the end?
Yeah, so that's yeah, we're going to get to all of this
stuff. Like I said, it got a little complicated because here's the
reality: מוקצה Muktzeh is scattered, so it's hard to ever wait, oh,
we're going to get to the prime location to discuss. I mean,
there are some thicker סוגיות sugyas of מוקצה Muktzeh than others, but
still, מוקצה Muktzeh is very, very scattered throughout. And also, what you're
getting a sense of is that the is Rabbi Shimon's position is
always very much up for grabs. The גמרא Gemara always says Rabbi
Shimon doesn't hold of מוקצה. Muktzeh. So as soon as you have
a position that says oh, this isn't the problem, oh, that's Rabbi
Shimon who doesn't hold of מוקצה. Muktzeh. But the reality is that
Rabbi Shimon does hold of a few cases of מוקצה. Muktzeh. So
exactly figuring out what Rabbi Shimon holds of when he doesn't hold
of is always also becomes complicated. But anyway, we will see a
lot more of this מוקצה Muktzeh scattered throughout. Okay, so now we
move on to the third פרק. perek. And this is the פרק
perek which really as you see, we're going from ערב שבת Erev
Shabbat preparations, lighting candles, and now putting stuff on the fire. Although
it's a little funny because it seemed from everything we saw before
that the fire stuff was arranged before and the candles were the
very last. Except not so clear because when we as one of
the ברייתות beraitot it said about what they did at the third
blow is that they said they got the stuff off the fire
and they lit the candles. So at least they're occurring at roughly
the same amount of time. But anyway, this is one the final
preparations is all about the food on the fire, which if you
remember from the end of the first פרק perek that בית הלל
Beit Hillel and בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, although בית הלל Beit Hillel
generally allows stuff to do מלאכה melacha starting from ערב שבת Erev
Shabbat and going into שבת, Shabbat, but by the food on the
fire, except with certain exceptions, he does not allow, and that has
to do with at least the גמרא Gemara explained it as a
concern that you would come to be anxious about it and stir
the and stir the coals. So this is going to be the
focus of that discussion about leaving food on the fire, which ultimately
as you know, gets to be our whole issue about having a
בלעך. blech. So let's take a look at what we have in
the משנה. Mishnah. Okay. כירה שהסיקוה בקש ובגבבא. Kira she-hisikuha be-kash u-ve-vivah.
So
you have a כירה. kira. A כירה kira was an oven that
basically, as רש"י Rashi says, was a you know, it's like a
huge pot, by which I mean that it was I'm sure that
they have a nice picture there of a כירה. kira. I actually
will bring in, I have a whole book which is called כלי
חרס בתקופת התלמוד. Klei Cheres BiTekufat HaTalmud. It's great bedtime. Anyway, so
it's a huge big book of like it goes through every single
pottery vessel and he has another book called כלי זכוכית בתקופת התלמוד.
Klei Zechochit BiTekufat HaTalmud. It's out of print, they're great books. So
it goes through every single, you know, vessel ever mentioned and gives
you like the archaeology and the picture and all the cases where
it's mentioned and whatever. What? Yeah. Anyway. So anyway, a כירה kira
is a just a huge, you know, pottery vessel, not vessel like
oven, it stayed fixed on the floor, and it was acted like
an open it was like a big pot, and you had the
fire on the inside, and you put your pot, your pot into
do we have a well, whatever, it's like putting a pot inside
of another pot. Okay. Yeah.
Well, I mean, I don't even know. It doesn't even require so
much, like imagine just without the without all this stuff in it.
Okay? So this was the so you had all this as the
fire, except it didn't go that high, and you put your other
pot, you put your pot pot on the lip and it was
supported by the lip and it was heated and it obviously did
a good job concentrating the heat. Okay? And that was how you
would cook on your כירה. kira. So what happened? You made the
fire with בקש ובגבבא, be-kash u-ve-vivah, which is basically straw and stubble.
Okay, now straw and stubble makes a quick flame, but what what
why is that not necessarily always the best material to use as
straw? It would burn out too quickly. Right. Won't last. More like
the fire dies out. Oh yeah, it would okay. So it would
so yeah, it would not last. So it burned out very quickly.
So therefore what happens? So there's no real there's contained heat in
it but there are no real coals. So if our concern is
about stirring the coals, that really is not a present concern. So
if you lit it up with this straw and stubble, נותנין עליה
תבשיל, notnin aleha tavshil, then you can put, no problem about putting
a pot on it before שבת. Shabbat. There's no concern of stirring
the coals. However, בגפת ובעצים, be-gefes u-ve-eitzim, if you did it with
the רש"י Rashi says גפת gefes is some type of a remnant
of like a sunflower seeds or עצים, eitzim, real sticks, you know,
then lo then and you really have now like some coals and
some, you know, stuff that still is there that has a lot
of contained heat. heat, in the actual fuel itself, in the actual
wood itself, then then there's a concern you put the stuff on
it, it's going to be cooking over שבת, Shabbos, you might come
to stir the coals. What would we say? לא יתן עד שיגרוף
או עד שיתן את האפר. lo yiten ad sheyigrof o ad sheyiten
es ha'eifer. Do not, you can't put the pot on until either
you sweep it out, so then it's like completely empty, so obviously
then it's just heat, but it's not, there's no coals there, or
you put ashes on it. And by putting ashes on it, therefore
it is you're basically killing the fire, so again there's nothing to
stir. Okay, that's what you have to do.
Now, בית שמאי אומרים, Beis Shammai omrim, so that's basically don't put
stuff on a actual present fire on שבת Shabbos that you might
come to stir the ashes. Don't put it from ערב שבת. erev
Shabbos. בית שמאי אומרים, Beis Shammai omrim, now let me just stop
here maybe for one second because I don't want to run to
the practical application but it's worth keeping it in mind. So if
that's true, the basic פשט pshat of all this
is you can't have a fire burning underneath your food, either it's
already burnt out, or you swept it out, or you've extinguished it,
so there's no fire burning. So how do we have a fire
burning with a בלעך? blech? So basically the גמרא Gemara is going
to discuss that the אפר eifer might not totally extinguish the fire.
What the אפר eifer might do is it might cover the fire,
it will be a היכר, heker, but we're not saying that when
you put on the the the ashes or the dirt it has
to totally extinguish the fire. And therefore that will translate into having
a fire burning with a בלעך blech on top. The בלעך blech
on top becomes like the אפר. eifer. Okay, it somewhat lowers the
heat, it is a היכר, heker, and even without completely removing the
fire that is enough. But the simple reading you would come away
from the משנה Mishna is there can't be any fire, and then
obviously you've got a big problem about what we do. Okay, but
that is not what's going to be the case. Now, בית שמאי
אומרים חמין אבל לא תבשיל ובית הלל אומרים חמין ותבשיל. Beis Shammai
omrim chamin aval lo tavshil u'Beis Hillel omrim chamin v'tavshil. בית שמאי
Beis Shammai says I allow you to put a pot of hot
water on with these conditions, but not but not like a stew.
And בית הלל Beis Hillel says water or stew. What's the difference?
Why would בית שמאי Beis Shammai be more lenient by water?
Water doesn't cook.
What? Just gets hot.
It does boil.
But you're not so anxious about, it's not a long ongoing process
and is it cooking well and you've got to check on it
and you've got to stir and all those types of things. Water
is much more simple, that he's not concerned about, that basically just
gets hot. But something that actually cooks and you're much more anxious
about, that is something that בית שמאי Beis Shammai will not allow
even with these conditions.
Meaning you can't put like pasta in your water.
Correct. Just plain water. ובית הלל אומרים חמין ותבשיל. u'Beis Hillel omrim
chamin v'tavshil. I don't care if it's water, I don't care if
it's something that you're actually cooking, תבשיל tavshil doesn't literally mean stew,
means something that you cook, something other than water, and it's okay.
Thankfully we פסק pasken like בית הלל. Beis Hillel. בית שמאי אומרים
נוטלין אבל לא מחזירין ובית הלל אומרים אף מחזירין. Beis Shammai omrim
notlin aval lo machzirin u'Beis Hillel omrim af machzirin. בית שמאי Beis
Shammai says you can take stuff off the fire but you can't
put it back on, presumably the stuff that I've allowed you to
keep on the fire, the hot water, allow you to keep it
on, but if you take it off on שבת Shabbos don't put
it back on. ובית הלל אומרים אף מחזירין. u'Beis Hillel omrim af
machzirin. Nope, the stuff you're allowed to keep on, when you take
it off you can put it back on. Okay, and that becomes
a whole issue of taking the טשולנט cholent pot off, taking טשולנט
cholent then putting the טשולנט cholent pot back on, which we'll see
in the גמרא. Gemara. Yes.
Is בית הלל Beis Hillel arguing on the pot of water or
on any cooked food? Because בית הלל Beis Hillel
presumably בית הלל's Beis Hillel saying that anything that I've allowed including
any cooked food you can take off and put back on. Okay,
so they're arguing within their own position of what they allow, whether
that also includes putting it back on. So בית שמאי Beis Shammai
says I only allow a small amount of things, only water and
only to put it on. ובית הלל u'Beis Hillel says I allow
a larger category, תבשיל, tavshil, all cooked things, and not only to
leave it on but also to return. Okay, so let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, says the גמרא,
Gemara, we raise the question האי לא יתן hai lo yiten when
it says don't put this on, לא יחזיר הוא? lo yachzir hu?
Does it mean, which is a very strange suggestion, does it mean
what we're going to get to at the end of the משנה,
Mishna, don't put it back on? So when we say don't, כירה,
kirah, when about putting stuff on unless you've swept it out or
whatever, it means you can't return it to the fire unless you've
swept it out. אבל לשהות, aval lish'hoses, to leave it on from
before שבת, Shabbos, okay by the way these become important nouns and
categories in this discussion, לשהות lish'hoses is שהייה, shehiya, לחזור lachazor is
חזרה. chazara. Okay, so שהייה shehiya means leaving it on from before
שבת, Shabbos, חזרה chazara means you took it off and you're putting
it back on. So maybe our משנה Mishna just means that when
you have to sweep it out that's only to put it back
on. אבל לשהות, aval lish'hoses, to leave it on, משהין אף על
פי שאינו גרוף וקטום. mash'hin af al pi she'eino garuf v'katum. Maybe
you can leave it on from before שבת Shabbos even if you
didn't sweep it out, even with a nice blazing fire. Why would
that be? ומני u'mani and ומני u'mani and who would our משנה
Mishna be? חנניה היא דתניא חנניה אומר כל שהוא כמאכל בן דרוסאי
מותר לשהותו על גבי כירה אף על פי שאינו גרוף וקטום. Chananya
hi d'tanya Chananya omer kol shehu k'ma'achal Ben Drusai mutar lish'hoso al
gabi kirah af al pi she'eino garuf v'katum. Once the food is
cooked to מאכל בן דרוסאי, ma'achal Ben Drusai, which is like a
half cooked or a third cooked, then you can keep it on
the oven from before שבת Shabbos even though it is not swept
out. So therefore maybe our משנה Mishna that demands sweep keeping it
out or קטום katum is putting ashes. קטם ketem
in Aramaic, קטם ketem is אפר, efer, is ashes. So when our
משנה mishna says about
putting ashes, so the verb it uses for is קטומה ketuma or,
you know, it means ashed if you made a verb out of
it, ashed. Okay, so anyway, so חנניה Hananya says even without sweeping
it out or putting on ashes, you can keep stuff once it's
already a half or a third cooked on an open fire. After
that stage you're not so anxious because it's edible anyway and therefore
you do not have to worry about it. Now, why should we
read the משנה mishna that way? Obviously, the simple sense is משנה
mishna is talking about שהייה shehiya and only mentions חזרה chazara at
the end. So take a very quick look at תוספות Tosfos top
of ל"ז ע"א. lamed zayin amud alef. תוספות Tosfos says לעולם אימא
לך להחזיר
תנן. l'olam eima lach l'hachzir tnan. It's going to be a long
discussion about whether the משנה mishna means להחזיר l'hachzir or לשהות. l'shahos.
תוספות Tosfos says משום דקיימא לן כחנניה כמו שיפורש בעזרת השם דחיק
לאוקמה מתניתין כחנניה. mishum d'kaima lan k'Hananya k'moshe puresh b'ezrat hashem dochik
l'okmah matnisin k'Hananya.
So תוספות'ס Tosfos's position and this is the opinion of the אשכנזים
Ashkenazim is that we פסקן pasken like חנניה. Hananya. And since we
פסקן pasken like חנניה, Hananya, look there's no question that our משנה
mishna much more פשט pshat is לשהות תנן, l'shahos tnan, that talking
about leaving it on from before שבת Shabbos and it only gets
to the idea of putting it back at the end of the
משנה, mishna, but because we פסקן pasken like חנניה Hananya says תוספות
Tosfos and therefore we פסקן pasken that to leave it on is
really totally okay without sweeping it out as long as it's a
third or half cooked. So we're trying to get the משנה mishna
to be consistent with that. And therefore the משנה mishna that insists
that it be swept out or, you know, ashes put on, that
is talking about to put it back. But in order to leave
it there, that would be allowed even if it's not swept out.
So I just want you to keep this in mind that for
the אשכנזים, Ashkenazim, this is the big debate of אשכנזים Ashkenazim and
ספרדים. Sefardim. אשכנזים Ashkenazim פסקן pasken like חנניה, Hananya, the ספרדים Sefardim
do not פסקן pasken like חנניה. Hananya. And this basically is the
question of once your food is on its good way to cooking
like half cooked, do you need a בלעך blech on ערב שבת?
erev Shabbos? And according to the אשכנזים, Ashkenazim, the real הלכה halacha
is that you do not. The only reason you need a בלעך
blech on ערב שבת erev Shabbos is if the food is started
cooked and not totally raw. You might remember before raw also isn't
a problem because then you forget about it till the next day.
So if not totally raw and it's not yet a half cooked,
that's when you need a בלעך. blech. But if it's either totally
raw or it is already half cooked from before שבת, Shabbos, the
only reason you would need a בלעך blech is להחזיר תנן. l'hachzir
tnan. The only reason according to חנניה Hananya you need a בלעך
blech once it got to half cooked is if you plan on
putting it back on the fire. So when we just got married,
you know, I was as my as a bachelor I
was following the אשכנזי Ashkenazi הלכה halacha and I would basically, you
know, not bother with a בלעך blech since I would not if
I wasn't going to put the food back on after, you know,
after on Friday night especially, you know, even though the רמ"א Rama
says it's better to be מחמיר לכתחילה machmir l'chatchila whatever. So anyway
certainly if it's pretty much fully cooked you don't need a בלעך.
blech. Everybody really agrees to that. So anyway, so I wouldn't have
a בלעך blech and let's just say that did not last too
long in my married life.
But anyway, but that will be the discussion that we will see
is about if the food is already half cooked, according to חנניה,
Hananya, you only need a בלעך blech להחזיר l'hachzir not לשהות. l'shahos.
So that's the question. Our משנה mishna sounds like you always need
to do גרופה וקטומה, grufa u'ketuma,
which for us means you need a בלעך. blech. Is that פשט?
pshat? Do you really always need it or not? Maybe we rule
like חנניה, Hananya, you really don't need it if it's already half
cooked and our משנה mishna is only talking about להחזיר תנן l'hachzir
tnan if you're coming to put it back on the fire. Yes?
So when you have a difference, an אשכנזי Ashkenazic ספרדי Sefardic difference,
could for instance a ספרדי Sefardi come and eat in an אשכנזי?
Ashkenazic?
All right, I'm not going to answer that. Okay, anyway, so, but
the basic answer is yes, but I'm not going to answer that.
So that's one question. Now I will say one other thing that's
important at this stage which is why is להחזיר l'hachzir a bigger
issue for חנניה? Hananya? If he's not concerned that you'll come to
stir it, why is it the concern that, you know, once it's
half cooked, why is it the concern that if you're putting it
back you'll come to stir it?
Because then it's cold, then they might want to, you know, they
might want some more, it's already gotten cold, you want to put
it back. What? And so meaning the food took off, it got
cold, you
put it back, it actually could be cold down. What we call
חזרה chazara is not what the משנה mishna calls חזרה. chazara. So
okay, but you're saying maybe it got cold down. Maybe. The more
issue is, the general explanation is that either that it heightens the
concern. Michael's saying, Michael's answer is okay, but it assumes a very
particular example that it did cool down.
The more explanation has to do with the act of returning, putting
it back. Why? The act of putting it back, this is sort
of like taking Michael's idea but broadening it a little bit, but
the act of putting it back, once you're in the process of
handling it already, you took it off, you put it down, you
put something back down, you say, oh you know what, the flame
needs to be a little higher. As opposed to like hands off,
right, you're not going to come and fiddle with it, I know
it's cooking, it's שבת, Shabbos, whatever, but once you're already dealing with
it and putting it on the fire, and also you forget, putting
it on the fire you forget it's שבת, Shabbos, you're putting something
on the fire. Okay, so that could lead to more likelihood of
A greater concern of stirring. And number two is, even if it
doesn't lead to a greater concern of stirring, it looks more like
cooking. Putting something on a fire feels like cooking. It's experientially מחזי
כמבשל, mechzi k'mevashel, is the phrase Rashi uses. It looks like, it
feels like, experientially it's much more closer to an act of cooking
and that's not something we want you to be doing on שבת.
Shabbos. Okay, so these are two different explanations which by the way
I can't help myself for to apply it להלכה למעשה, l'halacha l'maaseh,
but hopefully it will keep on going back to this, is an
important question also because of in order to put something back on
the flame, is it enough, can you do it on a hot
plate that let's say, I don't know, that has knobs that in
theory you could adjust? So the argument could be, well, if the
concern is it looks like it's cooking, nobody cooks on a hot
plate. So it doesn't look like it's cooking, right? If the concern
however is that you might come to, there's a greater concern you'll
come to adjust it, well, if this still has knobs and you
might come to adjust it, it'll still do cooking. Right. Okay, fine,
I'm giving an example this way. So the question becomes why is
להחזיר lehachzir a bigger issue? Is it a bigger issue because of
מחזי כמבשל mechzi k'mevashel or is it a bigger issue that you'll
come to stir? Mike's right, you could also do the flip. You
could have a case that you have your knobs covered, let's say
it's a crock pot. That's a flip case. You have your knobs
covered so there's not a concern you'll accidentally come to adjust it,
but maybe it's מחזי כמבשל mechzi k'mevashel because people do cook in
a crock pot so it feels like experientially like you're cooking. So
is the reason דחזרה d'chazara is more strict because of what it
looks like or because of the greater likelihood you'll come to stir?
And there are actual practical נפקא מינהs nafka mina between those two.
Okay, so anyway that is there, which we will get to, maybe.
So anyway, but so that is the issue. So let's take a
look on the גמרא. Gemara. So is the משנה Mishnah which says
you need to get rid of the flame talking about to put
it back where there's greater concerns and it's חנניא Chananya that would
say that to keep it on the flame is not an issue
if it's half cooked, the bigger issue is putting it back, או
דילמא, o dilma, or do you say לשהות תנן, l'shehot tnan, that
we're talking about the simple sense of the משנה, Mishnah, that we're
talking about just leaving it there and letting it you know,
for before שבת? Shabbos? And even though it's just leaving and you're
not putting it back, you have to sweep out the sweep out
the oven.
לשהות, L'shehot, now where am I?
I'm sorry, I just lost my page.
או דילמא לשהות תנן. O dilma l'shehot tnan. ואי גרוף וקטום אין,
Ve'ee garuf vekatum in, if it's swept out or ashes are put
on, yes. ואי לא לא, Ve'ee lo lo, and if not, no.
וכל שכן להחזיר, V'chol shekein lehachzir, and if you can't leave it
on, you certainly can't return it to the flame on שבת. Shabbos.
תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear, דתני תרי בבי במתניתין. detani
terei bavei bematnitin. Our משנה Mishnah has two sections. בית שמאי אומרים
חמים אבל לא תבשיל, Beis Shammai omrim chamim aval lo tavshil,
water yes, cooked things no. ובית הלל אומרים חמים ותבשיל, U'veis Hillel
omrim chamim vetavshil, water and cooked things. בית שמאי אומרים נוטלין אבל
לא מחזירין, Beis Shammai omrim notlin aval lo machzirin, you can take
but you can't put back. ובית הלל אומרים אף מחזירין, U'veis Hillel
omrim af machzirin, you can even put back. Now how would this
משנה Mishnah read according to the two possibilities? אי אמרת לשהות תנן,
Ee amrat l'shehot tnan, if you say it means to leave it
on, which is clearly פשט pshat in the משנה, Mishnah, הכי קתני,
hachi katani, then here's how you would read it. כשהסיקו בקש ובגבבא
משהין עליה תבשיל, Keshehishiku b'kash u'vigvava mashei'in aleha tavshil, you
can allow from before שבת Shabbos a cooked thing to remain on
it because there's no coals.
בגפת ובעצים לא ישהה עד שיגרוף או עד שיתן אפר, Begefet u've'eitzim
lo yeshahei ad sheyigrof o ad sheyitein eifer, until you sweep it
out or put the ashes because you're concerned you'll stir the coals.
And that's leaving it on from before שבת. Shabbos. ומה הן משהין,
U'mah hen mashei'in, what are you allowed to leave on from before
שבת? Shabbos? So that's a debate. בית שמאי אומרים חמים אבל לא
תבשיל, Beis Shammai omrim chamim aval lo tavshil, only hot water, not
cooked things. ובית הלל אומרים חמים ותבשיל, U'veis Hillel omrim chamim vetavshil,
water and cooked things. So that's about leaving it on. That's debate
number one. That's issue number one. You can leave it on if
you sweep it out, and what do you leave on is a
debate of בית הלל ובית שמאי, Beis Hillel u'veis Shammai, water or
other things. And then the משנה Mishnah goes on: וכי היכי דפליגי
לשהות
פליגי נמי להחזיר. U'che'heichi de'pligi l'shehot pligi nami lehachzir. And you know
what, there's also another debate about putting it back, שבית שמאי אומרים
נוטלין אבל לא מחזירין. she'Beis Shammai omrim notlin aval lo machzirin. בית
שמאי Beis Shammai will say what I allow you to leave on,
water, I'll only allow you to leave it on or to take
it off from the fire but I will not allow you to
put it back on the fire. ובית הלל אומרים, U'veis Hillel omrim,
בית הלל Beis Hillel says what I allow you to leave on,
water and תבשיל tavshil and cooked things, אף מחזירין, af machzirin, you
can even take it off and put it back. Okay, so the
whole משנה Mishnah is beautiful. First it says here's what you need
to leave it on. What can you leave on? בית הלל ובית
שמאי Beis Hillel u'veis Shammai disagree: water or other things. What about
putting it back? That's also a debate of בית הלל ובית שמאי.
Beis Hillel u'veis Shammai. Very nice simple three stages of the משנה.
Mishnah. אלא אי אמרת להחזיר תנן, Ella ee amrat lehachzir tnan, if
our משנה Mishnah is starting with the idea of putting it back,
הכי קתני, hachi katani, here's how you would read it.
כשהסיקו בקש ובגבבא מחזירין עליה תבשיל, Keshehishiku b'kash u'vigvava machzirin aleha tavshil,
then you can put stuff back on because there's nothing there.
בגפת ובעצים לא יחזיר עד שיגרוף או עד שיתן אפר, Begefet u've'eitzim
lo yachazir ad sheyigrof o ad sheyitein eifer, until you sweep it
out or cover the fire. Again, this would be חנניא, Chananya, so
to leave it on you could always leave it on once it's
half cooked, but the problem is you want to put it back
on. Then you need... to sweep it out. It has to have
been swept out from before.
ומאי מחזירין, u-mai machzirin, what could they put, what are you allowed
to put back on? בית שמאי אומרים חמין אבל לא תבשיל, Beit
Shammai omrim chamin aval lo tavshil, only water, ובית הלל אומרים חמין
ותבשיל, u-Beit Hillel omrim chamin ve-tavshil, water or cooked objects. So now,
בית שמאי אומרים נוטלין אבל לא מחזירין Beit Shammai omrim notlin aval
lo machzirin ובית הלל אומרים אף מחזירין. u-Beit Hillel omrim af machzirin.
So now when they're debating can you put stuff back on, אטו
למה לי? atu lama li? What's that adding to the debate? We've
already discussed putting it back on. We've already said if you want
to put it back on, you gotta sweep it out. What are
you allowed to put on? בית שמאי Beit Shammai says water, בית
הלל Beit Hillel says even cooked things. So now what are you
saying, oh by the way there's a debate of בית הלל Beit
Hillel ובית שמאי u-Beit Shammai if you can put stuff back on?
The only debate to be water versus other cooked things and we've
already said that. So the basic point is if until now we've
been talking about leaving it on, then you understand that the end
of the משנה mishnah introduces a new idea of putting it back
on. But if until now we've been talking about putting it back
on, so then what's being added by this last line in the
משנה mishnah that there's a debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel ובית
שמאי u-Beit Shammai putting it back on? So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara answers is, let's get a little bit into the דף.
daf. לעולם אימא לך le-olam eima lach I'll tell you להחזיר תנן
le-hachzir tnan that we are talking about putting it back on. וחסורי
מחסרא והכי קתני ve-chasuri me-chasra ve-hachi katani our משנה mishnah is missing
some words and here is how it would have to be read.
כירה שהסיקוה בקש ובגבבא מחזירין עליה תבשיל kira she-hisikuha be-kash u-ve-gvava machzirin
aleha tavshil
if you used again straw and stubble you can put it back
on. בגפת ובעצים לא יחזיר עד שיגרוף או עד שיתן אפר be-gefet
u-ve-etzim lo yachzir ad she-yigrof o ad she-yiten efer if it's with
wood you cannot put back on again like חנניה Chananya leaving it
on would be okay, but you cannot put it back on until
you sweep it out. אבל לשהות aval le-shaot but now we add
in a missing section. אבל לשהות aval le-shaot but if it's about
leaving it on משהין אף על פי שאינו גרוף ואינו קטום mash'hin
af al pi she-eino garuf ve-eino katum right we would sort of
insert this whole section into the משנה. mishnah. To leave it on,
that would be okay, even if you did not sweep it out.
This is חנניה Chananya once it's half cooked, you can leave it
on even if you did not sweep it out. ומאי משהין u-mai
mash'hin what could you leave on? בית שמאי אומרים חמין אבל לא
תבשיל Beit Shammai omrim chamin aval lo tavshil only water, ובית הלל
אומרים חמין ותבשיל u-Beit Hillel omrim chamin ve-tavshil
water and cooked objects. והחזרה דאמינא לך ve-ha-chazara de-amina lach
by the way, when we started the משנה mishnah and told you
you can put things back on if you swept it out, לאו
דברי הכל היא lav divrei ha-kol hi that's not a consensus, אלא
מחלוקת בית שמאי ובית הלל ela machloket Beit Shammai u-Beit Hillel that's
a debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel ובית שמאי. u-Beit Shammai. שבית
שמאי אומרים נוטלין ולא מחזירין she-Beit Shammai omrim notlin velo machzirin בית
שמאי Beit Shammai says that you can take but not put back,
ובית הלל אומרים אף מחזירין u-Beit Hillel omrim af machzirin you can
even put it back. So it's a very complicated read of the
משנה. mishnah. I am not, I would not be surprised if you
did not follow that, so let me try to rephrase that. But
the reason is because it's a very hard read of the משנה.
mishnah. The משנה mishnah clearly the פשט pshat is as the גמרא
Gemara said. You can leave stuff on the fire on the stove
if you swept it out. What can you leave? Debate of בית
הלל Beit Hillel ובית שמאי u-Beit Shammai water or other things. What
about putting it back? That's also a debate of בית הלל Beit
Hillel ובית שמאי. u-Beit Shammai. Very simple progression of the משנה. mishnah.
If you start by saying here's the conditions for putting it back,
then the end is not going to make sense because the end
reintroduces the whole putting it back. So here's how the גמרא Gemara
sets it. It starts by saying that you can put it back,
that here are the conditions for putting it back, it has to
be swept out. Okay, the middle that talks about water versus cooked
objects, that now is talking about it's talking about leaving it on.
To put it back it needs to be swept out. Leaving it
on like חנניה Chananya does not need to be swept out. But
what can you leave on? That's debated בית הלל Beit Hillel ובית
שמאי u-Beit Shammai water or other things. Then the last section of
the משנה mishnah says, oh by the way, remember the first section
where we said that you can put stuff back as long as
you swept it out? That's only בית הלל's Beit Hillel position. That's
only בית הלל's Beit Hillel position. בית שמאי Beit Shammai doesn't allow
you to ever put it back. Okay, so how do you have
the debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel ובית שמאי u-Beit Shammai in
the middle about water and other things? Because that was about leaving
it on. So you start, putting it back if you sweep it
out. At the end we're going to say that's only בית הלל,
Beit Hillel, not בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. בית שמאי Beit Shammai never
lets you put it back. And in the middle we're going to
have a debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel ובית שמאי u-Beit Shammai
about leaving it on where without sweeping it out and there even
and there בית שמאי Beit Shammai only allows water and בית הלל
Beit Hillel allows other things. Very complicated read of the משנה. mishnah.
The פשט pshat is as תוספות Tosafot says that the גמרא Gemara
is going through these hoops to try to get the משנה mishnah
to possibly read like חנניה Chananya and תוספות Tosafot says the reason
is because we פסקן pasken like חנניה. Chananya. The ספרדים Sefardim don't
agree with that, okay, but for whatever reason the גמרא Gemara is
explaining this so it's going to be tomorrow's דף daf it's going
to continue with whether it's לשהות ולהחזיר lish'hot u-lehachzir which will get
us to the core debate of חנניה וחכמים Chananya ve-Chachamim of once
something is a third or half cooked, can you leave it on
the fire ערב שבת erev Shabbat without needing a בלעך, blech, without
sweeping, without removing the flame and we will continue that tomorrow.
Since we don't hold like
חנניה. Chananya.